Guide to the Tamiment Library Web Collection on Labor Unions and Organizations WEB.ARC.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37, Local 983 Archived Website, Mar 28, 2014-ongoing; AFSCME. Local 983.
  AFSCME (American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees), Local 983 is one of the District Council 37's earliest locals, founded in the 1950s. The union initially represented motor vehicle operators, but came to include different blue collar employees, including high pressure plant tenders, parks workers, asbestos handlers, assistant city highway repairers, city seasonal aides and other municipal and public employee jobs. 1998-2013, Mark Rosenthal was elected president of Local 983. In 2013, Joe Puleo was elected president of the local. The website contains information on the union's benefits, contracts, and event listings.
  Motor vehicle drivers |z United States.
- American Federation of Teachers (AFT) Archived Website, Jun 18, 2011 - ongoing; American Federation of Teachers.
  The American Federation of Teachers (AFT), founded in 1916, represents the economic, social and professional interests of classroom teachers. It is an affiliated international union of the AFL-CIO. The AFT has more than 3,000 local affiliates nationwide, 43 state affiliates, and more than 1.5 million members. Five divisions within the organization represent the broad spectrum of AFT's membership: teachers; paraprofessionals and school-related personnel (PSRP); local, state and federal employees; higher education faculty and staff; and nurses and other healthcare professionals. In addition, the union includes more than 170,000 retiree members.
  Teachers' unions |z United States.
- American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) Archived Website, Jan 29, 2009 - Jul 11, 2012; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists.
  The American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), founded in 1937, is a national labor union representing performers, journalists and other artists working in the entertainment and news media. AFTRA's scope of representation covers broadcast, public and cable television, radio, sound recordings, “non-broadcast" and industrial material, as well as Internet and digital programming. AFTRA advocates on legislative and public policy issues that directly affect members’ wages and working conditions. This includes lobbying and support for such issues as ownership consolidation in the broadcast industry, Equal Employment Opportunity laws and regulations, copyright and performance rights issues, “non-compete" restrictions, OSHA and local safety regulations, and more. AFTRA also represents artists and journalists in judicial proceedings, often as amicus, and before the U.S. Copyright Office. In 2012, AFTRA merged with the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) to form SAGAFTRA.
  Radio broadcasting |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Television broadcasting |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.
- American Guild of Musical Artists (AGMA) Archived Website, Apr 28, 2009 - ongoing; American Guild of Musical Artists.
  The American Guild of Musical Artists, AFL-CIO (AGMA), founded in 1936, is an American labor union that represents 8,000 current and retired opera singers, ballet and other dancers, opera directors, backstage production personnel at opera and dance companies, and figure skaters. AGMA is a branch of Associated Actors and Artistes of America. The website contains auditions listings, agreements and contracts, news and event listings, and information on meetings and board members.
  Performing artists |x labor unions |z United States.
- American Guild of Variety Artists (AGVA) Archived Website, Apr 23, 2012 - ongoing; American Guild of Variety Artists.
  The American Guild of Variety Artists (AGVA) is an AFL-CIO-affiliated labor union founded in 1939 to represent performing artists and stage managers for live performances in the variety field. The variety area of performance includes singers and dancers in touring shows and in theatrical revues, theme park performers, skaters, circus performers, comedians & stand-up comics, cabaret & club artists, lecturers, poets, monologists, spokespersons, and variety performers working at private parties special events. AGVA is a branch of The Associated Actors and Artistes of America. AGVA negotiates contracts and provides relief for members. The website contains information on their relief funds, auditions, news, and other information.
  Entertainment industry.
- American Labor Studies Center (ALSC) Archived Website, Mar 5, 2012 - ongoing; American Labor Studies Center
  The American Labor Studies Center is a nonprofit organization whose mission is to collect, analyze, evaluate, create and disseminate labor history and labor studies curricula and related materials, aligned to the various state and national standards, to kindergarten through 12th grade teachers nationwide. They will include such areas as the history, organization, activities, and issues affecting the labor movement and the political, economic, and cultural aspects of workers and their unions. The ALSC sponsors workshops, courses, conferences and other events to acquaint teachers with the curriculum and related materials. The ALSC is located in Troy, New York in the Kate Mullany house. The website contains information for teachers, students, and unions.
  Labor |x History |z United States.
- American Postal Workers Union (APWU) Archived Website, Dec 5, 2009 - ongoing; American Postal Workers Union.
  The American Postal Workers Union (APWU), formed in 1971, represents more than 220,000 United States Postal Service employees and retirees, and nearly 2,000 private-sector mail workers. It represents employees of the United States Postal Service who are clerks, maintenance employees, and motor vehicle service workers. APWU works for decent pay, benefits, and safe working conditions for workers they represent. The APWU is a Union Network International and AFL-CIO affiliate.
  Postal service |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.
- American Rights at Work Archived Website, Dec 23, 2008 - Jan 1, 2014; American Rights at Work.
  American Rights at Work (ARAW), founded in 2003, is a U.S. nonpartisan, nonprofit organization that advocates for workers and their right to form unions without interference. ARAW is a labor policy and advocacy organization dedicated to educating the American public about the many barriers that workers face when they attempt to exercise their rights to organize and engage in collective bargaining. The organization conducts research into United States labor law and the National Labor Relations Board as they relate to unions, employer actions in union organizing, and collective bargaining campaign. ARAW’s resources include publications, Workers’ Rights Clearinghouse database, and Workers’ Rights Watch: Eye on the National Labor Relations Board. In December of 2013, American Rights at Work merged with Jobs with Justice.
  Employee rights |z United States.; Labor laws and legislation |z United States.; Labor movement |x Political activity |z United States.; Labor unions |z United States.
- American Social History Project Archived Website, Jul 6, 2012 - ongoing; City University of New York.
  The American Social History Project/Center for Media and Learning (ASHP/CML), founded in 1981, produces print, visual, and multimedia materials that explore the social and cultural history of the United States. They also lead development seminars. The website contains their digital projects, their “Who Built America?" series, documentaries, teaching services, and a their new media lab blog.
- Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) Archived Website, Mar 28, 2014-ongoing; Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance.
  Founded in 1992, the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA) was created to address the continued under-representation of Asian Pacific American (APA) workers in the labor movement and the specific challenges APA workers face. APALA works on projects related to voter registration, the DREAM Act, and workplace organizing. The website contains information on their executive board, youth leadership and organizing committees, press releases, news listings, convention information, and a blog.
  Asian American labor union members.; Asian Americans |x Civil rights.; Asian Americans |x Economic conditions.; Asian Americans |x Employment.; Asian Americans |x Politics and government.; Asian Americans |x Social conditions.
- Association for Union Democracy Archived Website, Feb 7, 2007 - ongoing; Association for Union Democracy.
  The Association for Union Democracy (AUD) is a pro-labor, non-profit organization dedicated solely to advancing the principles and practices of democratic trade unionism in the North American labor movement. AUD provides organizing, educational, and legal assistance to those working for greater membership control of their unions. AUD has operated several projects including, the Union Democracy Worker Education Project; the Women's Project; the Workers Rights Clinic; the AUD Steelworkers Fair Election Project; and the Longshore Workers Democracy Project.
  Labor union democracy |z Canada.; Labor union democracy |z United States.
- Association of Flight Attendants (AFA-CWA) Archived Website, Dec 5, 2009 - ongoing; Association of Flight Attendants
  The Association of Flight Attendants-CWA (AFA-CWA), founded in 1945, is a union representing flight attendants in the United States. In 2011, AFA represents nearly 60,000 Flight Attendants at 23 airlines, making it the world's largest Flight Attendant union. The goal of flight attendants who become part of AFA-CWA is to negotiate better pay, benefits, working conditions, work rules at their airline, and to improve their safety on the job. The AFA is part of the Communication Workers of America (CWA), an affiliate with the AFL-CIO, and an affiliate of the 5 million member International Transport Workers' Federation.
  Flight attendants |x Labor unions |z United States.
- Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco Workers and Grain Millers International Union (BCTGM) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco Workers and Grain Millers International Union
  The Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco Workers and Grain Millers' International Union (BCTGM) is a labor union in the United States and Canada with a membership of 100,000. The union includes workers in bakeries, candy, cereal, sugar, grain mills, tobacco plants, food processing and manufacturing facilities and other related occupations related to these industries. The union traces its history to the founding of the Journeymen Bakers Union in 1886. The contemporary BCTGM was formed in January, 1999 from the merger of the Bakery, Confectionery and Tobacco Workers' International Union and the American Federation of Grain Millers. The BCTGM is affiliated with the AFL-CIO, the Canadian Labour Congress and the International Union of Food Workers (IUF).
  Bakery employees |x Labor unions.; Tobacco workers |x Labor unions |z United States.
- Black Workers for Justice Archived Website, May 8, 2011 - ongoing; Black Workers for Justice
  The Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ) is a mass activist workers organization. It includes socialists, radical working class and general members, who link the immediate struggles in the workplaces and communities to a long term transitional radical program for Black empowerment/self-determination, social justice and social transformation. BWFJ was founded in 1981. Its labor and political perspectives grow out of an analysis of the development of the U.S. national and global economy, the U.S. imperialist state, and the ongoing role of the U.S. South as a fundamental pillar of U.S imperialism.
  African American labor union members.; Black nationalism.; Community organization.
- Brandworkers International Archived Website, May 12, 2012 - ongoing; Brandworkers International
  Founded in 2007, Brandworkers is a New York City-based organization that works to protect and advance the rights of retail and food employees. By training workers in social change tools and facilitating member-led workplace justice campaigns, Brandworkers promotes employer compliance with the law and challenges corporate misconduct in the community. The website contains information on campaigns and programs, news, and blog posts.
  Retail trade
- Bread and Roses Cultural Project Archived Website, Aug 9, 2009; 1199SEIU United Healthcare Workers East
  Bread and Roses, part of the 1199SEIU, was founded in 1979, as a cultural resource for union members and students in New York City who would otherwise have little access to the arts. Bread and Roses established the only permanent union exhibition space in the nation, Gallery 1199, at the union’s New York City headquarters. Bread and Roses appears to be defunct as of 2009.
  African American labor union members.; Hispanic American labor union members.; Labor in art.
- Bread and Roses Heritage Committee Archived Website, Sep 10, 2012 - ongoing; Bread and Roses Heritage Committee
  Bread and Roses Heritage Committee is the organizing committee for the annual Bread and Roses Labor Day Festival in Lawrence, Massachusetts. The festival was created in honor of the Bread and Roses strike in 1912. The website contains a schedule of events, news, and Lawrence labor history.
  Labor |x History |z United States.; Lawrence (Mass.); Textile Workers' Strike, Lawrence, Mass., 1912
- Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers Local 1 Archived Website, Dec 5, 2012 - ongoing; Bricklayers and Allied Craftworkers, Local 1
  The International Union of Bricklayers and Allied Craftsmen, Local 1 was granted a charter by the National Union of Bricklayers of the U.S.A. on October 17, 1868 in Brooklyn, New York and is one of the oldest continuously-existing locals in New York City. The union represents bricklayers, plasterers, stonesetters, and pointers, cleaners and caulkers. The website contains their newsletter, events, and news listings.
  Bricklayers |x Labor unions.
- Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen (BRS) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - ongoing; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen
  The Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen, founded in 1901, represents nearly 9,500 signal employees on both the freight railroads and the passenger and commuter railroads across the United States and into Canada. The Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen is affiliated with the AFL-CIO and the Transportation Trades Department.
  Railroads |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.
- Building and Construction Trades Department, AFL-CIO, (BCTD) Archived Website, Oct 25, 2012 - ongoing; The Building and Construction Trades Department, AFL-CIO
  The Building and Construction Trades Department, AFL-CIO, (BCTD) is the coordinating body of construction unions in the AFL-CIO. The department provides training and support to construction workers. It is made up of seven committees: Apprenticeship and Training; the Canadian Executive Board; General Presidents' Committee on Contract Maintenance; Labor-Management Committee; Legislative Task Force Committee; National Organizing Committee; and the Women in the Trades Committee. The website contains news, directories, legislative issues, and field services.
  Construction industry |x labor unions |z United States.
- Building Bridges Radio: Your Community & Labor Report Archived Website, Aug 9, 2009 - ongoing; Building Bridges Radio
  Building Bridges: Your Community and Labor Report is a labor news web blog and a weekly one hour program covering local, national and international labor and community issues over radio WBAI-Pacifica 99.5 FM. Besides covering labor issues, the website focuses on human rights abuses, environmental concerns, US political domination abroad, and other social justice issues.
  Labor movement |x Political activity |z United States.; Labor movement.; Labor radio stations |z United States.; Labor unions and radio |z United States.; Labor unions |z United States.; Labor unions.; News web sites |z United States.; Working class.
- Building Trades Employers' Association of the City of New York. Archived Website, Feb 1, 2009 - ongoing; Building Trades Employers' Association.
  Building Trades Employers Association (BTEA) is affiliated with 28 trade union contractor associations, representing the 1,700 construction managers, general contractors and specialty subcontractor firms in New York City, who employ 125,000 people. Members range in size from multi-billion dollar internationally recognized firms to small and mid-sized specialty trade contracting firms. The BTEA promotes safety, skill training, professional standards, and works to strengthen the economic vitality and social fabric of New York City.
  Building trades |z New York (State) |z New York.; Employers' associations |z New York (State) |z New York.
- California Nurses Association/National Nurses Organizing Committee (CNA/NNOC) Archived Website, Dec 4, 2009 - Dec 27, 2011; California Nurses Association/National Nurses Organizing Committee
  Founded in 1903, the California Nurses Association, and its national arm, the National Nurses Organizing Committee is a labor organization of registered nurses and health care unions. CNA/NNOC has 86,000 members in 50 states, representing nurses at scores of hospitals, clinics, and home health agencies. Since 2000, over 19,000 RNs at 50 hospitals have elected to affiliate with CNA. CNA/NNOC is also a founding member of the 150,000-member National Nurses United.
  Nurses |x Labor unions |z California.; Nurses |x Labor unions |z United States.
- Caucus of Rank-and-File Educators Archived Website, Sep 12, 2012 - ongoing; Caucus of Rank-and-File Educators
  The Caucus of Rank and File Educators (CORE) is a coalition within the Chicago Teacher’s Union that took power in the union in 2010. They are against school privatization and led the 2012 Chicago teacher’s strike. The website contains news updates and a newsletter.
- Center For Labor Renewal Archived Website, May 5, 2011 - ongoing; Center for Labor Renewal
  The Center for Labor Renewal, launched in 2006, is a think tank dedicated to combining different threads of working class organizing and activism to promote the transformation and renewal of labor as a progressive social movement in this country and internationally.
  Labor movement.; Research institutes.
- Center for Study of Working Class Life Archived Website, May 3, 2011 - ongoing; Center for the Study of Working Class Life
  The Center for Study of Working Class Life, founded by the faculty and staff at the State University of New York at Stony Brook, in November, 1999, explores the meaning of class in the present day. The center studies social questions, including the gap between the rich and the poor, the attack on government programs through privatization, and other questions. The Center studies class mainly with tools of the social sciences, but also uses the arts as a tool of study.
  Labor |x Education.; Working class |x Education.; Working class |z United States |x History
- Change to Win Archived Website, Dec 3, 2009 - ongoing; Change to Win Federation.
  Change to Win Strategic Organizing Center is a coalition of American labor unions formed in 2005. The coalition currently consists of four member unions: The International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT); Service Employees International Union (SEIU); United Farm Workers (UFW); and United Food and Commercial Workers (UFCW) and supports 5.5 million workers.
- Chicago Teachers Union Archived Website, Sep 13, 2012 - ongoing; Chicago Teachers Union
  The Chicago Teacher’s Union, chartered in 1937, represents 30,000 teachers and educational support personnel working in the Chicago Public Schools. The Chicago Teachers Union is an organization of educators dedicated to advancing and promoting quality public education, improving teaching and learning conditions, and protecting members' rights. They are affiliated with the Chicago Federation of Labor (CFL), the Illinois State Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (ISFL-CIO), the American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), the Illinois Federation of Teachers (IFT), and the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). The website contains news, events, and information on their 2012 strike.
- Chinese Staff Workers Association Archived Website, Sep 25, 2007 - ongoing; Chinese Staff Workers Association.
  Chinese Staff & Workers' Association (CSWA) was formed in New York City in 1979, to support over 1,300 workers from various trades and ages, injured and non-injured, documented and undocumented workers. It primarily assists workers in restaurants, the garment and construction industries, although it is active among workers in a variety of professions. The organization serves workers from all backgrounds, most of its members are Chinese and most of its efforts directed at employers in Chinatown.
  Chinese American labor union members.; Chinese Americans |x Civil rights |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Civil Service Merit Council Archived Website, Feb 6, 2009 - Mar 6, 2009; Civil Service Merit Council.
  The Civil Service Merit Council, founded in 1971, is a non-partisan coalition of individuals and organizations whose primary purpose was to increase the level of efficiency and integrity of government. The Merit Councils primary objective is to ensure that all appointments to the New York civil service shall be made through competitive examinations to properly classified positions from among persons duly qualified without regard to race, religion, age, sex, or political opinion or affiliation. The Council is dedicated to preserving and advancing the rights and tenure of all persons in the Merit System.
  Civil service |z New York (State) |z New York.; Municipal officials and employees |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Civil Service Technical Guild, Local 375, DC 37, AFSCME - AFL-CIO Archived Website, Mar 5, 2009 - ongoing; AFSCME, Local 375.
  The Civil Service Technical Guild (Local 375, DC 37), founded in 1929, represents 7,000 engineers, architects, scientists, chemists, planners, and other technical inspectors working for the City of New York. The guild’s goals include the prevention of the outsourcing city contracts, fighting for the adherence to civil service laws, enforcing contracts, and fighting privatization. The union is affiliated with the ASFCME and the AFL-CIO.
  Architects |z New York (State) |z New York.; Civil engineers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Collective bargaining |x Engineers.; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Coalition of Black Trade Unionists Archived Website, Sep 25, 2007 - ongoing; Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (U.S.).
  The Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (CBTU), founded in 1972, consists of members from seventy-seven international and national unions with fifty chapters across the country. It is the independent voice of black workers within the trade union movement, challenging organized labor to be more relevant to the needs and aspirations of black and poor workers.
  African American labor union leaders.; African American labor union members.
- Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions Archived Website, Jul 9, 2011 - Jul 8, 2013; Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions